Guide to the Houston Theater Program Collection, 1839-2008 MS 359
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Houston Theater Program Collection
1839-2008
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Davis, John Blodgett
MS 359
2 Linear Feet (4 boxes)
This collection of play programs and related printed publications was created and maintained mainly by John Blodgett Davis and reflects the Houston, Texas theater scene primarily in the 1950s and 1960s.
Biographical Note
The city of Houston has been a home to theater almost since its founding, with the first professional production on June 11, 1838. Since then, the Houston Theater District has grown until it seats the second largest number of people in the country, behind only New York. In 1951, "Houston was the site…of The Playhouse, the first permanent building built in America specifically to be a theatre-in-the-round" (Dauphin, 83). Another historic venue is the Alley Theatre whose growth mirrors that of Houston theatre, evolving from one simple room to hosting two main stages holding 824 and 310 seats. Productions at the Alley tended to be popular, modern plays early on, and it was only later that they leaned towards the classics. Other venues today include the "national AIA prize-winning Jesse H. Jones Hall for the Performing Arts" (Holmes 2), the Miller Outdoor Theatre, and the Hobby Center for the Performing Arts. The Hobby Center is home to Theatre Under The Stars, the "largest non-profit producer of musical theater in America" (About).
Houstonian Ed Oppenheimer collected these programs from the 1900s to the 1990s from various theaters in Houston as well as New York, London, Dallas, and Fort Worth.
Scope and Contents
This collection of play programs and related printed publications was created and maintained mainly by John Blodgett Davis and reflects the Houston, Texas theater scene primarily in the 1950s and 1960s
Access Restrictions
This material is open for research.
Conditions Governing Access
Stored off-site at the Library Service Center. Please request this material via woodson@rice.edu or call 713-348-2586.
Acquisition Information
John Blodgett Davis material- gift of Nell Willman; other material- unknown (January 1955; February 1961 (?); Bob Patten, 2008.
Index Terms
Subjects
Theater
Document Types
articles
Places
Texas; Houston (Tex.) -- History.; Art
- Series I: Houston Theater Programs, 1839-2008, 22455
  - Alley Theater, 1961, 1992, 1999; 22472 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bienvenue Theatre, 36966 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Civic-Community Concert Association, 1938-1949, 22471 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Community Players, 1938-1942 and undated, 22470 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Garden Theater, 1951, 22469 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Houston Fringe Theater Festival, 36967 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Houston Players, Inc., 1949, 22468 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Little Room Downstairs Theater, 1998-99; 36968 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Little Theater of Houston, 1933-1940, 22467 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Little Theater of Houston, 1941-1945, 22466 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Little Theater of Houston, 1945-51 and undated, 22465 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Lyric Theater of Houston, n.d., 22464 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Main St. Theater, 2008; 36969 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Metropolitan Theater, 1950 (2 items), 22463 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Majestic Theater (4 items), 22462 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Music Hall, 1941-1953 (24 items), 22461 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Playhouse Theater, 1951-53 (16 items), 22460 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Edna W. Saunders presents, 1929-1952 (76 items), 22459 (Box 2, Folder 5-7)
  - Scottish Rite Cathedral, 1932-1937 (10 items), 22458 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Stages Repertory Theatre, 1999; 36970 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Temple League Players, 1940-41 (6 items), 22457 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Theater Lab Houston, 1999; 36971 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Various theaters, 1839-1954 (56 items), 22456 (Box 2, Folder 12-13)
- Series II: Theater Scrapbooks (Houston, Chicago, NYC, Minneapolis), 1911-1917, 22453
  - Theater Scrapbooks (2), 22454 (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
- Series III: Houston society, arts and entertainment publications, 1938-1957, 22447
  - The Daily Courier, Dec. 26, 1938, 22452 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Entre-Nous: Houston's Journal of Interesting Events and Fascinating People, Vol. I no. 1—14; Vol. II no. 1,2,7 (1957), 22451 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Junior League, 1920s-1950s, 22450 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Houston Downtowner, Vol. I no. 1-24, 1947-1948, 22449 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Houston – This Week, Vol. I no. 1-4; Vol. II No. 1-2, 1950, 22448 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Series IV: New York Theater Programs, 1923-1954, 22444
  - Century Theater, "Aphrodite", New York City, 1923?, 22446 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - New York City theater programs, 1950-54, 22445 (Box 4, Folder 2-3)